Guide to the Charles R. Walgreen Foundation Records 1938-1956
University of Chicago Library
Charles R. Walgreen Foundation. Records
1938-1956
2.5 linear ft. (5 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Charles R. Walgreen Foundation for the Study of American Institutions was established in June 1937 to foster greater appreciation of American life and values among University of Chicago students. Funding awarded to the University of Chicago by the foundation was meant to support scholarships, teaching, research, and public lectures. Contains correspondence, lecture notices, notes on the history of the Foundation, biographical information on Charles Walgreen, and research reports by students who held Walgreen scholarships. Also contains typescripts and transcripts of lectures given under the auspices of the Foundation. Includes material that relates to the Walgreen Scholarship Fund, Walgreen Scholars, grants awarded to the Committee on Human Development, and suggested speakers and series. Correspondents include Dean Acheson, Vannevar Bush, Edward S. Corwin, Herbert Hoover, Walter Lippman, Leverett Saltonstall, Adlai Stevenson, Allen Tate, Henry A. Wallace, and others.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions.
Historical Note
The Charles R. Walgreen Foundation for the Study of American Institutions was established in June, 1937 when Walgreen, who felt that there was need for a greater appreciation of the American way of life among University of Chicago students, gave the University $550,000 for this purpose. Although the funds have been used to support scholarships, teaching, and research in the various fields of American studies, the Foundation has perhaps been best known for the many series of public lectures which it has sponsored. Over the years, people of outstanding accomplishment in public life and in the academic world of the social sciences and the humanities have been brought to the campus to speak on various aspects of American institutions and values; among the speakers have been Walter Lippmann, Carl Sandburg, Jaques Maritain, Ralph Bunche, George Kennan, Paul Douglas, Hannah Arendt, and Jacques Barzun.
Scope Note
Contains correspondence, lecture notices, notes on the history of the Foundation, biographical information on Charles Walgreen, and research reports by students who held Walgreen scholarships. Also contains typescripts and transcripts of lectures given under the auspices of the Foundation. Includes material that relates to the Walgreen Scholarship Fund, Walgreen Scholars, grants awarded to the Committee on Human Development, and suggested speakers and series. Correspondents include Dean Acheson, Vannevar Bush, Edward S. Corwin, Herbert Hoover, Walter Lippman, Leverett Saltonstall, Adlai Stevenson, Allen Tate, Henry A. Wallace, and others.
The documents in the collection have been arranged in five manuscript boxes. The first box contains general correspondence of the Foundation, as well as correspondence concerning the Foundation's grants to the Committee on Human Development, the Walgreen Scholarship Fund, and the Walgreen Scholars. In the second box is correspondence concerning the lecture series. The third box contains correspondence dealing with suggested speakers and series; letters from distinguished people who were unable to accept invitations extended by the Foundation; and several folders of miscellanea, including lecture notices, correspondence concerning the publication of lectures, notes on the history of the Foundation, biographical information about Charles Walgreen, and several research reports by students who held Walgreen scholarships. The fourth and fifth boxes contain typescripts and transcripts of twelve series of lectures given under the auspices of the Foundation.
The papers in this collection are from the files of the Foundation, and cover the period from 1938 to 1956. They were deposited in the University Archives by the Department of Political Science in September, 1962. It should be mentioned that the correspondence and records of the Foundation for the period prior to 1940 are not complete; some of the material was lost when the Foundation moved its files in 1945.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/theart.html
Subject Headings
Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Bush, Vannevar, 1890-1974; Corwin, Edward Samuel, 1878-1963; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974; Saltonstall, Leverett, 1892-; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965; Tate, Allen, 1899-; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965; Walgreen, Charles R.; Charles R. Walgreen Foundation for the Study of American Institutions; University of Chicago. Committee on Human Development; University of Chicago. Committee on Human Development -- History; United States -- Study and teaching; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations
INVENTORY
- Series I: Correspondence
  - General correspondence 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Human Development 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Human Development 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Walgreen Scholarship Fund 1941-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Walgreen Scholars 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Walgreen Scholars 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Walgreen Scholars 1943-1944; 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Walgreen Scholars 1945-1946; 1946-1947; 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Walgreen Scholars 1948-1949; 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Walgreen Scholars 1950-1951; 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Lecture series, Correspondence
  - Series of 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Series of 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Series of 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Series of 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Series of 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Series of 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Series of 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Series of 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Series of 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Series of 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Series of 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Series of 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Series of 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Series of 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Series of 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Series of 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Series of 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Proposed Speakers and Series 1941-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Proposed Speakers and Series 1949-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Autograph letters, Dean Acheson, April 20, 1948, 1 p., April 26, 1948, 1 p. Mortimer Adler, July 12, 1946, 1 p. Henry A. Barton, November 24, 1944, 2 p. Hugo L. Black, June 25, 1948, 1 p. Chester Bowles, May 5, 1948, 1 p., May 29, 1953, 1 p. Van Wyck Brooks, October 3, 1948, 2 p. Vannevar Bush, October 23, 1944, 1 p., November 13, 1944, 1 p. Jefferson Caffery, April 7, 1955, 1 p. Edward S. Corwin, February 15, 1949, 2 p., February 26, 1949, 2 p., March 7, 1949, 2 p., January 4, 1950, 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Autograph letters, Elmer Davis, April 26, 1948, 1 p. Gordon Dean, February 19, 1954, 1 p. Thomas E. Dewey, June 2, 1947, 1 p. L. W. Douglas, May 13, 1952, 1 p. M. S. Eccles, June 7, 1948, 1 p. Dwight D. Eisenhower, May 24, 1948, 1 p. Henry Ford II, October 30, 1952, 1 p. William T. Gossett, July 7, 1953, 1 p. Ralph H. Gabriel, July 31, 1948, 1 p., October 19, 1948, 1 p. C. H. Greenewalt, February 11, 1952, 1 p. R. G. Gustavson, July 22, 1953, 1 p. George H. Guttridge, January 25, 1943, 1 p., February 19, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Autograph letters, W. Averell Harriman, June 10, 1953, 1 p. Eli F. Hecksher, December 7, 1950, 1 p. Leon Henderson, May 23, 1946,1 p., May 27, 1948, 1 p. Pendleton Herring, May 11, 1946, 1 p., June 27, 1946, 1 p. Calvin Hoover, June 19, 1948, 3 p. Herbert Hoover, December 5, 1940, 1 p., July 16, 1948, 1 p., September 25, 1948, 1 p. Hiram W. Johnson, December 14, 1940, 1 p. V. O. Key, Jr., June 17, 1953, 1 p., July 2, 1953, 1 p. Arthur Krock, January 7, 1954, 1 p. Robert M. La Follette Jr., April 18, 1947, 1 p., May 22, 1947, 1 p. David E. Lilienthal, July 20, 1948, 1 p., January 20, 1950, 1 p. Walter Lippman, September 5, 1945, 1 p., February 5, 1955, 1 p., May 2, 1955, 1p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Autograph letters, Archibald MacLeish, March 13, 1946, 1 p. John J. McCloy, March 15, 1955, 1 p. Brien McMahon, October 17, 1946, 1 p. Carl Mayer, May 22, 1953, 1 p. Lewis Mumford, March 12, 1955, 1 p. John Courtney Murray, S. J., February 14, 1955, 2 p., April 18, 1955, 1 p. Thomas E. Murray, February 15, 1955, 1 p. Edward R. Murrow, April 20, 1953, 1 p. Henry Alonzo Myers, August 27, 1945, 1 p. Allan Nevins, April 19, 1939, 1 p., May 8, 1939, 1 p., March 3, 1952, 1 p. Reinhold Niebuhr, July 3, 1950, 1 p. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Autograph letters, Michael Oakeshott, March 1, 1950, 1 p. Beardsley Ruml, April 14, 1948, 1 p. Dean Rusk, March 21, 1952, 1 p., March 28, 1952, 1 p. Leverett Saltonstall, June 25, 1947, 1 p., June 30, 1947, 1 p., February 17, 1948, 1 p., April 13, 1948, 1 p. Harold D. Smith, July 19, 1946, 1 p., August 2, 1946, 1 p. Harold E. Stassen, August 9, 1947, 1 p. Adlai E. Stevenson, December 10, 1952, 1 p., June 21, 1953, 1 p. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Autograph letters, Allen Tate, April 27, 1953, 1 p., August 14, 1954, 1 p., January 11, 1955, 1 p., June 3, 1955, 1 p. Sol Tax, August 9, 1953, 2 p. Deems Taylor, January 11, 1954, 1 p. Carl Van Doren, April 13, 1948, 1 p. Henry A. Wallace, May 22, 1946, 1 p., June 26, 1946, 1 p., October 4, 1946, 1 p., October 11, 1946, 1 p. Barbara Ward, April 28, 1953, 2 p. Earl Warren, July 9, 1947, 1 p. Henry M. Wriston, February 21, 1944, 1 p. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Publication correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publicity: lecture notices (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - History of Walgreen Foundation (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Charles R. Walgreen: Biographical information (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Walgreen Scholarship Studies (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series III: Lecture series, Transcripts and Typescripts
  - Walter Lippmann, American Destiny. Winter, 1938, I."The Shattered International Order." February 16 II."The British Decline.'' February 17 III."The American Succession.'' February 18 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Walter Lippmann: American Destiny. Winter, 1938, I."Next Steps in Financing the War," February 5, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 1a)
  - George Fort Milton, American Institutions in War Congested Production Areas. Summer, 1944, I."The General Problem.'' July 17 II."Remedial Measures.'' July 18 III."The Problems of Decongestion.'' July 19 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Charles E. Merriam, Physics and Politics. Spring, 1947, I."The Beginning or the End?'' April 22 II."Will the New Physics Bring New Freedom or New Slavery?'' April 29 III."The Anatomy of the Atomic Energy Authority'' May 6 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Charles E. Merriam, Physics and Politics. Spring, 1947, IV."National Sovereignty and World order'' May 13 V."A World Bill of Rights'' May 20 VI."On the Agenda of Physics and Politics'' May 27 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Charles E. Merriam, An Analysis of Some Political Personalities I Have Known. Spring, 1948, I."President Wilson and Candidate Bryan.'' April 13 II."President Taft and President Hoover.'' April 20 III."Theodore Roosevelt and Franklin D. Roosevelt.'' April 27 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Charles E. Merriam, Physics and Politics. Spring, 1947, IV."Lawmakers: Senators Norris, Byrnes and Smith.'' May 6 V."Mayors and Managers.'' May 11 VI."Some Bosses on My List.'' May 18 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M. S. Szymczak, The Federal Reserve System; Problems and Policy. Winter, 1949, I."Monetary and Credit Problems.'' March 9 II."Federal Reserve Policy to Date.'' March 11 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Leo Strauss, Natural Right and History. Autumn, 1949, I."Natural Right and the Historical Approach.'' October 17 II."Natural Right and the Distinction between Facts and Values.'' October 19 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Leo Strauss, Natural Right and History. Autumn, 1949, III."The Origin of the Idea of Natural Right.'' October 21 IV."Classic Natural Right.'' October 24 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Leo Strauss, Natural Right and History. Autumn, 1949, V."Modern Natural Right.'' October 26 IV."The Crisis of Modern Natural Right and the Turn Toward History October 28 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - David Morris Potter, Economic Abundance and American Character. Autumn, 1950, I."Old and New Concepts of National Character.'' November 20 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - David Morris Potter, Economic Abundance and American Character. Autumn, 1950, II."Abundance, Status, and Mobility.'' November 22 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - David Morris Potter, Economic Abundance and American Character. Autumn, 1950, III."The Politics of Abundance: Democracy.'' November 24 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - David Morris Potter, Economic Abundance and American Character. Autumn, 1950, IV."Abundance and the Frontier Hypothesis.'' November 27 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - David Morris Potter, Economic Abundance and American Character. Autumn, 1950, V."The Institution of Abundance: Advertising.'' November 29 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - David Morris Potter, Economic Abundance and American Character. Autumn, 1950, IV."Abundance and America's World Outlook.'' December 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Paul Douglas, Economy and the Federal Budget. Autumn, 1951, I."The Theory, Size and Composition of the Federal Budget.'' October 23 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Paul Douglas, Economy and the Federal Budget. Autumn, 1951, II."Possible Economies in the Nondefence Budget.'' October 24 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Paul Douglas, Economy and the Federal Budget. Autumn, 1951, III."Possible Economies in the Military Budget.'' October 25 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Paul Douglas, Economy and the Federal Budget. Autumn, 1951, IV."Is There Any Hope for Economy?'' October 26 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Hans Simons, America's Stake in Western Germany. Winter, 1952, I."The Military Government: Germany's Defeat and Its Long-Range Consequences.'' February 11 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hans Simons, America's Stake in Western Germany. Winter, 1952, II."The Political Government: Occupation Purposes and Results.'' February 13 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Hans Simons, America's Stake in Western Germany. Winter, 1952, III."The Innate Conflicts: Basic Agreements and Disagreements Among the Allies.'' February 15 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hans Simons, America's Stake in Western Germany. Winter, 1952, IV."The Open Break: Germany Restored and Divided.'' February 18 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hans Simons, America's Stake in Western Germany. Winter, 1952, V."Defensive Democracy: The Development of West German Government.'' February 20 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hans Simons, America's Stake in Western Germany. Winter, 1952, VI."More Questions Than Answers: Germany as an Ally.'' February 22 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - John Hallowell, The Moral Foundations of Democracy. Spring, 1952, I."Democracy: Fact or Fiction?'' April 7 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - John Hallowell, The Moral Foundations of Democracy. Spring, 1952, II."Democracy as the Art of Compromise.'' April 9 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - John Hallowell, The Moral Foundations of Democracy. Spring, 1952, III."The Institutional Framework of Democracy.'' April 11 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - John Hallowell, The Moral Foundations of Democracy. Spring, 1952, IV."Democracy and Liberalism.'' April 14 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - John Hallowell, The Moral Foundations of Democracy. Spring, 1952, V."Human Nature and Politics.'' April 16 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - John Hallowell, The Moral Foundations of Democracy. Spring, 1952, VI."The Moral Foundation of Democracy.'' April 18 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Robert A. Horn, Freedom of Association in American Constitutional Law. Spring, 1953, I."Freedom of Association: The Growth of a Modern Liberty'' April 21 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Robert A. Horn, Freedom of Association in American Constitutional Law. Spring, 1953, II."Religious Freedom: An Old Tradition in a New Setting.'' (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Robert A. Horn, Freedom of Association in American Constitutional Law. Spring, 1953, III."Church and State: An American Experiment.'' April 23 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Robert A. Horn, Freedom of Association in American Constitutional Law. Spring, 1953, IV."The Lesson of Labor: In Union There is Strength.'' April 28 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Robert A. Horn, Freedom of Association in American Constitutional Law. Spring, 1953, V."The Political Party: From Private Club to Public Concern.'' April 30 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Robert A. Horn, Freedom of Association in American Constitutional Law. Spring, 1953, VI."Subversive Associations: Worms in the Entrails of Leviathan.'' May 1 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Meyer Kestnbaum, Business and Society. Winter, 1954, I."The Characteristics of an Industrial Society.'' February 1 II."The Role of Business in the Modern World.'' February 3 III."Business as a Social Force.'' February 5 (Box 5, Folder 19)